(Watch on www.kisskh.club Support Admin)
(شاهد على www.kisskh.club دعم الإدارة)
[Pursuit of Jade]
[السعي وراء اليشم]
[Episode 34]
[الحلقة 34]
Your Majesty, Prime Minister Wei and Grand Tutor Li request an audience.
صاحب الجلالة، رئيس الوزراء وي والمعلم الأكبر لي يطلبان مقابلة.
Dear ministers,
أيها الوزراء الكرام،
what brings you to see me?
ما الذي دفعك لرؤيتي؟
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
I wish to impeach Prime Minister Wei's son, Wei Xuan,
أرغب في عزل وي شوان، نجل رئيس الوزراء وي.
for forcibly levying winter grain, oppressing the people into revolt,
بسبب فرض ضرائب قسرية على محاصيل الحبوب الشتوية، وقمع الشعب ودفعه إلى الثورة،
and deserting the army.
والفرار من الجيش.
After returning to the capital without permission,
بعد عودته إلى العاصمة بدون إذن،
he treated human life as worthless.
لقد كان يعامل حياة الإنسان على أنها لا قيمة لها.
If he is not punished for all these crimes,
إذا لم يُعاقب على كل هذه الجرائم،
Heaven will not tolerate it!
لن يتسامح السماء مع ذلك!
Grand Tutor, don't be so hasty.
يا معلمنا الكبير، لا تتسرع.
What do you mean by treating human life as worthless?
ماذا تقصد بمعاملة حياة الإنسان على أنها بلا قيمة؟
Prime Minister Wei!
رئيس الوزراء وي!
Your son broke my young grandson's leg.
لقد كسر ابنك ساق حفيدي الصغير.
He might be crippled for the rest of his life!
قد يُصاب بالشلل لبقية حياته!
Was that a counter-stratagem,
هل كانت تلك حيلة مضادة؟
or is he innocent and actually deserves credit?
أم أنه بريء ويستحق التقدير فعلاً؟
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
If there is someone in our court
إذا كان هناك شخص ما في محكمتنا
who wields unchecked power and cannot be criticized,
الذي يمتلك سلطة مطلقة ولا يمكن انتقاده،
then I will have no choice
حينها لن يكون لدي خيار
but to beat the Petition Drum
لكن لقرع طبول العريضة
and let the world judge!
وليحكم العالم!
Well...
حسنًا...
Fine.
بخير.
I am willing to join you.
أنا على استعداد للانضمام إليكم.
Don't...
لا...
Your Majesty, for the sake of your dignity,
جلالتكم، من أجل كرامتكم،
I have endured all kinds of humiliation.
لقد تحملت كل أنواع الإذلال.
But Li Huaiqin
لكن لي هوا تشين
claims that my wife and I are on bad terms
يزعمون أن علاقتي بزوجتي سيئة
and that my son is a bastard!
وأن ابني ابن زنا!
He even says
بل إنه يقول
that I still love my childhood sweetheart,
أنني ما زلت أحب حبيبة طفولتي،
and that my true love is in the harem!
وأن حبي الحقيقي موجود في الحريم!
Such remarks
مثل هذه التصريحات
involve the late Emperor
إشراك الإمبراطور الراحل
and many secrets of the harem.
والعديد من أسرار الحريم.
And now the Li family is making presumptuous speculations.
والآن، تُطلق عائلة لي تكهناتٍ متغطرسة.
Fine.
بخير.
I will accompany you to the Petition Drum,
سأرافقكم إلى طبلة العريضة،
and we'll make everything
وسنصنع كل شيء
perfectly clear
واضح تمامًا
in front of the whole world!
أمام العالم أجمع!
Let's go!
دعنا نذهب!
You are talking nonsense!
كلامك هراء!
When did the Li family ever speculate about you and the ha...
متى تساءلت عائلة لي عنك وعن...
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
I didn't!
لم أكن!
-I didn't, Your Majesty! -You just said that!
-لم أفعل يا جلالة الملك! -أنت قلت ذلك للتو!
And now you're denying it?
والآن تنكر ذلك؟
Ministers, please don't get angry.
أيها الوزراء، من فضلكم لا تغضبوا.
Let's talk this over calmly.
دعونا نتحدث في هذا الأمر بهدوء.
Grand Tutor Li constantly spreads slander in court.
المعلم الكبير لي ينشر الافتراءات باستمرار في المحكمة.
I fear even Your Majesty finds it hard to judge fairly.
أخشى أن جلالتكم تجد صعوبة في الحكم بإنصاف.
You must explain this clearly!
يجب عليك شرح هذا بوضوح!
Let's go!
دعنا نذهب!
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
Ministers!
أيها الوزراء!
I am wrongly accused!
أنا متهم ظلماً!
Who accused you wrongly?
من الذي اتهمك ظلماً؟
It is clearly Wei Yan who deceives everyone
من الواضح أن وي يان هو من يخدع الجميع
and has no respect for you, Your Majesty!
ولا يكنّ لك أي احترام يا صاحب الجلالة!
-Your Majesty! -Don't let it cause a rift between you!
-جلالتك! -لا تدع ذلك يتسبب في حدوث شرخ بينكما!
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
Fine! Since you won't listen,
حسناً! بما أنك لا تستمع،
I won't be the Emperor anymore!
لن أكون الإمبراطور بعد الآن!
-I'll just abdicate! Alright? -Stop it!
- سأتنازل عن العرش! حسناً؟ - توقف عن ذلك!
You cannot!
لا يمكنك!
As the Emperor,
بصفته الإمبراطور،
how can you take off your dragon robe so easily?
كيف يمكنك خلع رداء التنين الخاص بك بهذه السهولة؟
Presumptuously!
بوقاحة!
How dare you, Wei Yan!
كيف تجرؤ يا وي يان!
How dare you speak so arrogantly to His Majesty!
كيف تجرؤ على التحدث بهذه الغطرسة إلى جلالته!
I think you're the one who is acting
أعتقد أنك أنت من يقوم بالتمثيل
presumptuously!
بوقاحة!
I was wrong, Your Majesty.
كنت مخطئاً يا جلالة الملك.
Alright, alright.
حسناً، حسناً.
You two were just acting in the heat of the moment.
لقد كنتما تتصرفان فقط في لحظة انفعال.
So was I.
وأنا كذلك.
In short,
باختصار،
it is all because Li Huaiqin lacked virtue after drinking
كل ذلك بسبب افتقار لي هواي تشين للفضيلة بعد شربه الخمر
and spoke recklessly.
وتحدث بتهور.
But since his leg is already broken
لكن بما أن ساقه مكسورة بالفعل
and he has been punished,
وقد عوقب،
I will send a royal physician to treat him.
سأرسل طبيباً ملكياً لعلاجه.
After he recovers,
بعد أن يتعافى،
he will be sent to the Imperial College to study and repent
سيتم إرساله إلى الكلية الإمبراطورية للدراسة والتوبة
to cultivate his character.
لتنمية شخصيته.
As for Wei Xuan injuring someone...
أما بخصوص قيام وي شوان بإيذاء شخص ما...
although there were extenuating circumstances,
على الرغم من وجود ظروف مخففة،
the state has its laws.
للدولة قوانينها.
Use of private punishment is wrong.
إن استخدام العقاب الخاص أمر خاطئ.
I... I will remove him from his post as Military Commissioner for now.
سأعزله من منصبه كمفوض عسكري في الوقت الحالي.
He can atone for his crimes by earning merits in the future.
بإمكانه التكفير عن جرائمه من خلال اكتساب أعمال صالحة في المستقبل.
Anyway,
على أي حال،
if I hear any more filthy rumors
إذا سمعت المزيد من الشائعات القذرة
concerning the reputation of the royal family,
فيما يتعلق بسمعة العائلة المالكة،
do not blame me for showing no mercy.
لا تلوموني على عدم إظهار الرحمة.
-Yes, Your Majesty!
- نعم يا جلالة الملك!
Your Majesty...
جلالتكم...
Your Majesty. Gone.
جلالتك. رحلت.
Your Majesty, please quell your anger!
جلالتك، أرجوك اهدأ من غضبك!
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
in this case,
في هذه الحالة،
Grand Tutor Li might become alienated from us.
قد ينعزل المعلم الكبير لي عنا.
Then what do you think I should have done?
إذن، ما رأيك فيما كان ينبغي عليّ فعله؟
Tell me!
أخبرني!
What should we do?
ماذا ينبغي علينا أن نفعل؟
Now that Xie Zheng is back,
الآن وقد عاد شيه تشنغ،
Wei Yan has become emboldened!
لقد ازداد وي يان جرأة!
Wei Yan came here today
جاء وي يان إلى هنا اليوم
clearly to slap me in the face
من الواضح أنه يريد أن يصفعني على وجهي
and break our alliance with Grand Tutor Li!
وكسر تحالفنا مع المعلم الكبير لي!
These two old turtles.
هاتان السلحفتان العجوزتان.
It's always one side overpowering
دائماً ما يكون أحد الجانبين هو المسيطر
the other between these two.
والآخر بين هذين الاثنين.
When will a third party
متى سيقوم طرف ثالث
get involved?
هل ترغب بالمشاركة؟
My Lord, what did His Majesty say?
يا سيدي، ماذا قال جلالته؟
That useless trash, Qi Sheng.
ذلك الهراء عديم الفائدة، تشي شنغ.
Such a fence-sitter. He changed his mind.
يا له من متردد! لقد غيّر رأيه.
Well...
حسنًا...
Now that Xie Zheng has returned,
والآن بعد عودة شيه تشنغ،
Wei Yan has become even more powerful.
لقد أصبح وي يان أكثر قوة.
It seems we can no longer rely on His Majesty.
يبدو أننا لم نعد نستطيع الاعتماد على جلالته.
The Li family
عائلة لي
must find another way out.
يجب إيجاد مخرج آخر.
Master,
يتقن،
Qi Min is likely to make a big move soon.
من المرجح أن يقوم تشي مين بخطوة كبيرة قريباً.
Also,
أيضًا،
there's news regarding the past events in Jinzhou that
هناك أخبار تتعلق بالأحداث الماضية في جينتشو
the Prime Minister ordered to be investigated.
أمر رئيس الوزراء بالتحقيق معه.
[To Grand Tutor, My Lord: I have been tirelessly investigating day and night,]
[إلى المعلم الأكبر، يا سيدي: لقد كنت أبحث بلا كلل ليلاً ونهاراً،]
The news came from Chongzhou.
جاء الخبر من تشونغتشو.
[and have finally uncovered a key clue in the old case, going back 17 years,]
[وقد كشفوا أخيراً عن دليل رئيسي في القضية القديمة، التي يعود تاريخها إلى 17 عاماً]
[concerning the troop deployment Tiger Tally]
[بشأن نشر القوات - تعداد النمور]
[once held by Wei Qilin, a household general of the Wei family.]
[كانت في السابق مملوكة لـ وي تشيلين، وهو قائد عسكري في عائلة وي.]
Do you think
هل تعتقد
we should inform the Eldest Young Master?
هل ينبغي لنا إبلاغ السيد الشاب الأكبر؟
Seventeen years ago,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً،
the Tiger Tally that Wei Qilin used to deploy the troops was real.
كان إحصاء النمور الذي استخدمه وي تشيلين لنشر القوات حقيقياً.
But it became a fake when it reached Lord Changxin.
لكنها أصبحت مزيفة عندما وصلت إلى اللورد تشانغشين.
Between the real and fake Tiger Tallies,
بين عدادات النمور الحقيقية والمزيفة،
the most critical link
الرابط الأكثر أهمية
was the person who delivered it.
كان هو الشخص الذي قام بتسليمها.
Wei Qilin.
وي تشيلين.
[Wei Residence]
[سكن وي]
After all these days,
بعد كل هذه الأيام،
you finally have the courage to come back.
أخيرًا لديك الشجاعة للعودة.
I heard Mother is ill.
سمعت أن أمي مريضة.
I was worried about her.
كنت قلقاً عليها.
As for Li Huaiqin's leg...
أما بالنسبة لساق لي هوا تشين ...
I'll take responsibility for my own actions.
سأتحمل مسؤولية أفعالي.
Take responsibility?
هل تتحمل المسؤولية؟
Are you worthy of taking responsibility
هل أنت جدير بتحمل المسؤولية؟
for the Wei family's lost honor?
من أجل شرف عائلة وي الضائع؟
And are you really capable of it?
وهل أنت قادر على ذلك حقاً؟
I've taken care of
لقد اعتنيت بـ
the official procedures.
الإجراءات الرسمية.
But you can't avoid
لكن لا يمكنك تجنب ذلك
the family punishment.
العقاب العائلي.
Guards.
حراس.
Here!
هنا!
Twelve!
اثنا عشر!
Thirteen!
ثلاثة عشر!
Fourteen!
أربعة عشر!
Fifteen!
خمسة عشر!
Sixteen!
ستة عشر!
Seventeen!
سبعة عشر!
Eighteen!
ثمانية عشر!
Punishment complete.
تم تنفيذ العقوبة.
Father.
أب.
Mother is sick.
الأم مريضة.
Won't you go and keep her company?
ألن تذهب وتؤنسها؟
I have had someone fetch a royal physician.
لقد طلبت من أحدهم إحضار طبيب ملكي.
Do you know why
هل تعرف لماذا
I broke Li Huaiqin's leg that day?
لقد كسرت ساق لي هوا تشين في ذلك اليوم؟
He insulted me.
لقد أهانني.
He said I'm not your son!
قال: أنا لست ابنك!
He said that your true love is your childhood sweetheart
قال إن حبك الحقيقي هو حبيب طفولتك
who's in the harem now.
من هم الموجودون في الحريم الآن؟
My mother
أمي
has been serving you all these years
لقد كنا نخدمكم طوال هذه السنوات
and gave everything for you.
وقدّم كل شيء من أجلك.
But now that she lies sick in bed,
لكن الآن وقد أصبحت طريحة الفراش بسبب المرض،
you can't even spare a glance for your wife?
ألا تستطيع حتى أن تلقي نظرة على زوجتك؟
Prime Minister.
رئيس الوزراء.
A letter from Wei Sheng.
رسالة من وي شنغ.
It concerns the Marquis of Wu'an.
الأمر يتعلق بماركيز ووآن.
See?
يرى؟
I have official affairs to handle.
لديّ أمور رسمية يجب عليّ إنجازها.
As for your mother,
أما بالنسبة لوالدتك،
take good care of her.
اعتني بها جيداً.
If there is nothing else,
إذا لم يكن هناك شيء آخر،
stay put
ابقَ في مكانك
and don't wander around.
ولا تتجول في الأنحاء.
You have only ever had Xie Zheng in your heart!
لم يكن في قلبك سوى شي تشنغ!
Have you ever considered Mother and me as family?
هل سبق لك أن اعتبرتني أنا وأمي عائلة؟
I guessed right.
لقد خمنتُ بشكل صحيح.
You care for Xie Zheng
أنت تهتم بـ شيه تشنغ
like he's your own.
كأنه ابنك.
You poured all your energy
لقد بذلت كل طاقتك
and all your care
وكل عنايتك
into him alone.
فيه وحده.
And I...
وأنا...
I can only watch helplessly from the sidelines!
لا يسعني إلا أن أشاهد عاجزاً من المدرجات!
Have you ever really looked at me?
هل سبق لك أن نظرت إليّ حقاً؟
Even once,
ولو لمرة واحدة،
just once?
مرة واحدة فقط؟
What I hate most
أكثر ما أكرهه
is this indifferent look of yours!
هذا هو تعبيرك اللامبالي!
Since I was little,
منذ صغري،
no matter what I did,
بغض النظر عما فعلته،
you never cared!
لم تهتم أبداً!
Is Xie Zheng your son,
هل شيه تشنغ ابنك؟
or am I?
أم أنني كذلك؟
Am I just a bastard you took in?
هل أنا مجرد ابن غير شرعي استقبلتموه؟
Am I?
هل أنا كذلك؟
You are not a child anymore.
أنت لم تعد طفلاً.
[Where Compassion and Grace Meet]
[حيث تلتقي الرحمة والنعمة]
The Princess Royal is here!
الأميرة الملكية هنا!
Your Highness,
صاحب السمو،
His Majesty is busy with state affairs.
جلالته مشغول بشؤون الدولة.
Please calm your anger, Your Majesty!
أرجو منك أن تهدأ من غضبك يا جلالة الملك!
I couldn't stop Her Highness!
لم أستطع إيقاف صاحبة السمو!
Never mind.
لا تهتم.
I didn't expect you to stop her.
لم أتوقع منك أن توقفها.
Leave us.
اتركنا.
Yes, Your Majesty.
نعم يا جلالة الملك.
Brother, I heard you want to marry me off to the Marquis of Wu'an?
يا أخي، سمعت أنك تريد أن تزوجني من ماركيز ووآن؟
Sister,
أخت،
I've found you a peerless hero for a husband.
لقد وجدت لك زوجاً بطلاً لا مثيل له.
Why are you displeased?
لماذا أنت مستاء؟
I'll beat you to death!
سأضربك حتى الموت!
Stop beating me, Sister!
توقفي عن ضربي يا أختي!
Don't run!
لا تركض!
It hurts!
إنه مؤلم!
Didn't you say you liked the Marquis of Wu'an before?
ألم تقل من قبل أنك معجب بماركيز ووآن؟
And that you wanted to marry him?
وأنكِ كنتِ تريدين الزواج منه؟
I was only 6 then!
كان عمري حينها ست سنوات فقط!
Six years old!
ست سنوات!
-You just want to get the Marquis of Wu'an on our side! -Sister!
- أنتِ تريدين فقط أن تجعلي ماركيز ووآن في صفنا! - أختي!
-Stop beating me! -Taking my marriage as an excuse!
- توقف عن ضربي! - اتخذ زواجي ذريعة!
It won't look good if you keep beating me!
لن يكون الأمر جيداً إذا استمريت في هزيمتي!
You care about that?
هل يهمك ذلك؟
First you sold me to the Li family,
أولاً بعتني لعائلة لي،
and now you're selling me to the Xie family.
والآن تبيعني لعائلة شي.
Am I still the Princess Royal?
هل ما زلتُ الأميرة الملكية؟
Don't I deserve any dignity?
ألا أستحق أي كرامة؟
You are a Qi too.
أنت أيضاً من نوع تشي.
Can you really bear to watch me
هل تستطيع حقاً أن تتحمل مشاهدتي؟
be manipulated by those two old bastards?
هل يمكن التلاعب بنا من قبل هذين العجوزين الحقيرين؟
I've been living in fear all this time,
لقد عشت في خوف طوال هذا الوقت،
and it has been 17 years, Sister.
وقد مرّت 17 سنة يا أختي.
Sister, you are well-read.
يا أختي، أنتِ واسعة الاطلاع.
Have you ever seen such a cowardly emperor as me?
هل رأيتم يوماً إمبراطوراً جباناً مثلي؟
Xie Zheng is not Wei Yan.
Xie Zheng ليس وي يان.
Even without a marriage alliance as leverage,
حتى بدون تحالف زواج كوسيلة ضغط،
he can still be of use to you.
لا يزال بإمكانه أن يكون مفيداً لك.
Then, Sister,
ثم يا أختي،
can you vouch for him forever?
هل يمكنك أن تضمن له الخير إلى الأبد؟
Lord Changxin...
اللورد تشانغشين...
Seventeen years ago, Lord Changxin...
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً، اللورد تشانغشين...
never imagined he would rebel either.
لم أتخيل أبداً أنه سيتمرد أيضاً.
Didn't they say
ألم يقولوا
his entire family was dead?
هل ماتت عائلته بأكملها؟
Then how... how did this story end up
إذن كيف... كيف انتهت هذه القصة
with Sui Yuanhuai faking his death and escaping?
هل قام سوي يوانهواي بتزييف موته والهروب؟
Anyway,
على أي حال،
stop playing matchmaker.
توقف عن لعب دور الخاطب.
Or I'll come back again.
وإلا سأعود مرة أخرى.
This time in the army,
هذه المرة في الجيش،
I may not have learned much else,
ربما لم أتعلم الكثير غير ذلك،
but I've learned
لكنني تعلمت
how to fight.
كيفية القتال.
Alright, I get it. I'm scared.
حسناً، فهمت. أنا خائف.
Go get Li Xiang immediately!
اذهبوا وأحضروا لي شيانغ فوراً!
Hurry!
عجل!
Losing an ear
فقدان الأذن
won't kill him!
لن يقتله!
[Wei Residence]
[سكن وي]
[Received Grace, Cherished Favor]
[نعمة مُنحت، فضلٌ عزيز]
Prime Minister, please save me.
يا رئيس الوزراء، أرجوك أنقذني.
Someone wants to depose me.
هناك من يريد عزلي.
Prime Minister,
رئيس الوزراء،
I'll be obedient from now on.
سأكون مطيعاً من الآن فصاعداً.
All that happened in the past
كل ذلك حدث في الماضي
was because I was deceived by the Li family.
كان ذلك بسبب تعرضي للخداع من قبل عائلة لي.
Prime Minister!
رئيس الوزراء!
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
Your Majesty, as the Emperor,
جلالتكم، بصفتكم الإمبراطور،
you should conduct yourself with proper dignity.
ينبغي عليك أن تتصرف بكرامة لائقة.
How can you lose your composure like this?
كيف يمكن أن تفقد أعصابك هكذا؟
Are rebel forces at the gates,
هل قوات المتمردين على الأبواب؟
or is someone staging a coup?
أم أن أحدهم يدبر انقلاباً؟
Neither.
لا.
The Palace still stands, and the walls are intact.
لا يزال القصر قائماً، والجدران سليمة.
Then why are you so panicked, Your Majesty?
إذن لماذا أنت مذعورٌ إلى هذا الحد يا جلالة الملك؟
I—I've lost my composure.
لقد فقدت أعصابي.
Li Xiang returned from Jizhou
عاد Li Xiang من Jizhou
and said that rumors were spreading in the army
وقال إن الشائعات تنتشر في الجيش
that a descendant of the former Eastern Palace had appeared.
أن أحد أحفاد القصر الشرقي السابق قد ظهر.
Seventeen years ago,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً،
you did everything to put me on the throne.
لقد فعلت كل شيء لتضعني على العرش.
I know that in this world,
أعلم أنه في هذا العالم،
only you will always stand on my side.
أنت وحدك من ستقف دائمًا إلى جانبي.
I trust no one but you.
لا أثق بأحد سواك.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
Prime Minister.
رئيس الوزراء.
I... I am truly flustered.
أنا... أنا مرتبك حقاً.
Rumors regarding the former Eastern Palace
شائعات بشأن القصر الشرقي السابق
have surfaced several times over the last decade.
وقد ظهرت عدة مرات خلال العقد الماضي.
I will handle it.
سأتولى الأمر.
However, Your Majesty,
لكن يا جلالة الملك،
the late Emperor abdicated to you,
لقد تنازل لك الإمبراطور الراحل عن العرش،
and you inherited the throne legitimately.
وقد ورثت العرش بشكل شرعي.
What is there to worry about?
ما الذي يدعو للقلق؟
Your Majesty, you must not forget
جلالتك، يجب ألا تنسى
that this time in the Northwest,
هذه المرة في الشمال الغربي،
there is a new general with outstanding merit
هناك جنرال جديد يتمتع بجدارة استثنائية
who saved the people from suffering
الذي أنقذ الناس من المعاناة
and won their hearts.
وفاز بقلوبهم.
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
you must take this opportunity to win her over.
يجب عليك اغتنام هذه الفرصة لكسب قلبها.
Only then can you reassure the people
عندها فقط يمكنك طمأنة الناس
and demonstrate your authority.
وأظهر سلطتك.
Prime Minister, you mean that butcher girl, Fan Changyu?
رئيس الوزراء، هل تقصد تلك الفتاة الجزارة، فان تشانغيو؟
This woman is indeed brave
هذه المرأة شجاعة حقاً
and did kill Lord Changxin on the battlefield.
وقتل اللورد تشانغشين في ساحة المعركة.
But she comes from humble origins
لكنها تنحدر من أصول متواضعة
and has no foundation in court.
وليس له أساس في المحكمة.
How could she be of use to me?
كيف يمكن أن تكون مفيدة لي؟
Don't forget,
لا تنسى،
she commands half the forces in Jizhou,
هي تقود نصف القوات في جيتشو،
and the Li family wants to win her over.
وتريد عائلة لي كسب ودها.
If you can summon her to the capital to reward her
إذا استطعت استدعاءها إلى العاصمة لمكافأتها
for her repeated military achievements,
نظراً لإنجازاتها العسكرية المتكررة،
it will demonstrate your vast grace.
سيُظهر ذلك كرمك العظيم.
Alright.
على ما يرام.
Excellent.
ممتاز.
Then I will follow your suggestion
سأتبع اقتراحك إذن
and issue my decree immediately,
وأصدر مرسومي فوراً،
summoning Fan Changyu and the generals who earned merit in quelling the rebellion
استدعاء فان تشانغيو والجنرالات الذين استحقوا الفضل في قمع التمرد
to the Capital to receive their rewards.
إلى العاصمة لاستلام مكافآتهم.
Great Yin now has its first mighty female general.
أصبح لدى يين العظمى الآن أول جنرال أنثى قوية.
I will personally hold the investiture ceremony for them.
سأقوم شخصياً بإقامة حفل التنصيب لهم.
Your Majesty, you're truly wise.
جلالتك، أنت حكيم حقاً.
The Qi family is full of lies.
عائلة تشي مليئة بالأكاذيب.
They're all equally despicable.
جميعهم بغيضون بنفس القدر.
You must be careful, Prime Minister.
يجب أن تكون حذراً يا رئيس الوزراء.
Even the Emperor knows about the former Eastern Palace.
حتى الإمبراطور يعلم بأمر القصر الشرقي السابق.
Is he planning to stop hiding it?
هل ينوي التوقف عن إخفاء الأمر؟
Is Xie Jiuheng
هل شيه جيوهينج
trying to become the next Wei Yan?
هل تحاول أن تصبح وي يان القادم؟
His Majesty decrees:
أصدر جلالته المرسوم التالي:
The rebellious Lord Changxin plotted against the western borders.
تآمر اللورد تشانغشين المتمرد ضد الحدود الغربية.
The female general Fan Changyu fought valiantly
قاتلت الجنرال فان تشانغيو ببسالة
and executed the rebel leader on the battlefield.
وأعدم زعيم المتمردين في ساحة المعركة.
I commend her achievements
أشيد بإنجازاتها
and hereby appoint her as Flower-Crowned General,
وبموجب هذا، يتم تعيينها جنرالاً متوجة بالزهور،
rank Fourth Grade,
الصف الرابع،
with a Purple-gold Fish Pouch.
مع حقيبة سمك ذهبية بنفسجية اللون.
You are to enter the Capital to pay your respects
يجب عليك دخول العاصمة لتقديم احترامك
and receive your title.
واستلم لقبك.
Flower-Crowned General!
أيها الجنرال المتوج بالزهور!
Look here!
انظر هنا!
So this is the Capital.
إذن هذه هي العاصمة.
Look at these buildings,
انظر إلى هذه المباني،
this road, and these people.
هذا الطريق، وهؤلاء الناس.
Mancang, pinch me.
مانكانج، قرصني.
Am I dreaming?
هل أنا أحلم؟
It hurts. We're not dreaming.
الأمر مؤلم. لسنا نحلم.
Behave yourselves.
التزموا بحسن السلوك.
Don't let people see
لا تدع الناس يرون
that we're from the countryside.
أننا من الريف.
So what?
وماذا في ذلك؟
Fan carved her way to her position as General
شقت فان طريقها إلى منصبها كجنرال
from the countryside with a butcher knife.
من الريف بسكين جزار.
Who dares look down on her?
من يجرؤ على الاستخفاف بها؟
Look at our female general. She's so cool.
انظروا إلى قائدتنا. إنها رائعة للغاية.
If General Fan were a man,
لو كان الجنرال فان رجلاً،
I'd want to marry him.
أرغب في الزواج منه.
Maybe General Fan has brothers?
ربما يكون للجنرال فان إخوة؟
If I can't marry her, being her sister-in-law would be fine too.
إذا لم أستطع الزواج منها، فسيكون من الجيد أيضاً أن أكون أخت زوجها.
I never imagined that on horseback,
لم أتخيل ذلك أبداً على ظهر الخيل،
she'd look more handsome than young men.
ستبدو أجمل من الشباب.
I heard His Majesty
سمعت جلالته
will personally hold the investiture ceremony.
سيتولى شخصياً إقامة حفل التنصيب.
Really?
حقًا؟
General Fan is mighty!
الجنرال فان قوي!
General Fan!
مُعجب عام!
[Guo's Wine House]
[بيت نبيذ غو]
His Majesty has decreed
أصدر جلالته مرسوماً
that Li Huai'an, Discipline Inspector of Jizhou,
أن لي هوايان، مفتش الانضباط في جيتشو،
and Flower-Crowned General Fan Changyu are to pay their respects.
وسيقوم الجنرال فان تشانغيو، الحائز على وسام الزهور، بتقديم واجب الاحترام.
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[مجتهد وفاضل]
Long live Your Majesty.
عاش جلالتكم.
You may rise.
يمكنك النهوض.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
شكراً لك يا صاحب الجلالة.
My beloved ministers, take a look.
أيها الوزراء الأعزاء، ألقوا نظرة.
These are the backbone of our Great Yin.
هذه هي الركائز الأساسية لـ "يين العظيم" لدينا.
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[مجتهد وفاضل]
I am unworthy of such praise.
أنا لا أستحق هذا الثناء.
To serve Your Majesty with loyalty
أن أخدم جلالتكم بإخلاص
is a subject's duty.
هو واجب على الرعية.
Moreover, in this battle against the rebels,
علاوة على ذلك، في هذه المعركة ضد المتمردين،
those with the greatest merit
أولئك الذين يتمتعون بأكبر قدر من الجدارة
were General He and the Marquis of Wu'an.
كان الجنرال هي وماركيز ووآن.
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[مجتهد وفاضل]
General He and the Marquis of Wu'an
الجنرال هي وماركيز ووآن
are indeed the pillars of Great Yin.
إنها بالفعل ركائز الين العظيم.
General He died in battle at Lucheng.
توفي الجنرال هي في معركة لوتشنغ.
I am heartbroken.
قلبي مفطور.
I couldn't eat for days.
لم أستطع تناول الطعام لأيام.
Fortunately, Great Yin has the Marquis of Wu'an
لحسن الحظ، لدى يين العظيم ماركيز ووآن
and loyal subjects like you.
ورعايا مخلصين مثلك.
That's why these ministers and I can rest easy.
ولهذا السبب يمكنني أنا وهؤلاء الوزراء أن نرتاح.
I will not fail your expectations, Your Majesty.
لن أخيب ظنك يا صاحب الجلالة.
I heard that among the people of Great Yin,
سمعت أن بين أهل يين العظيم،
a female general has emerged.
لقد برزت جنرال أنثى.
Step forward and let me see.
تقدم للأمام ودعني أرى.
I, Fan Changyu,
أنا، فان تشانغيو،
greet Your Majesty.
تحية لجلالتكم.
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[مجتهد وفاضل]
Come closer.
اقترب.
I, Fan Changyu, greet Your Majesty.
أنا، فان تشانغيو، أحيي جلالتكم.
Raise your head.
ارفع رأسك.
What a fine warrior peony.
يا لها من زهرة الفاوانيا المحاربة الرائعة.
Are you married?
هل أنت متزوج؟
Your Majesty, I already have a husband.
جلالتك، لدي زوج بالفعل.
Where is your husband now?
أين زوجك الآن؟
During the conscription early this year,
خلال فترة التجنيد الإجباري في مطلع هذا العام،
my husband went to the front lines.
ذهب زوجي إلى الخطوط الأمامية.
I was desperate to find him
كنت أتوق بشدة للعثور عليه
and joined the army by accident on the way.
وانضم إلى الجيش بالصدفة في الطريق.
But the Battle of Lucheng was too brutal.
لكن معركة لوتشنغ كانت وحشية للغاية.
My husband...
زوجي...
remains missing.
لا يزال مفقوداً.
Missing, you say?
تقول إنه مفقود؟
Then why don't you...
فلماذا لا تفعل ذلك...
In my 17 years on the throne,
خلال سنواتي السبعة عشر على العرش،
I have never seen a female general.
لم أرَ قط جنرالاً أنثى.
I was just overcome with emotion.
لقد غمرتني المشاعر.
Fan, in quelling the rebellion,
فان، في قمع التمرد،
killed Shi Hu first,
قتل شي هو أولاً،
and then beheaded Lord Changxin.
ثم قام بقطع رأس اللورد تشانغشين.
Her contribution is truly remarkable.
إن مساهمتها رائعة حقاً.
I hereby appoint her as Flower-Crowned General,
أُعيّنها بموجب هذا جنرالاً متوجاً بالزهور،
and bestow upon her the title of Imperial Madame of the Fourth Rank.
ومنحها لقب السيدة الإمبراطورية من الرتبة الرابعة.
Why is she conferred such a high rank?
لماذا مُنحت هذه الرتبة العالية؟
What happened?
ماذا حدث؟
I, Fan Changyu,
أنا، فان تشانغيو،
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[مجتهد وفاضل]
thank Your Majesty for your great grace.
أشكر جلالتكم على كرمكم العظيم.
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
since the founding of our dynasty,
منذ تأسيس سلالتنا،
there has never been a female general
لم يسبق أن تولت امرأة منصب جنرال.
holding a rank above the fifth grade.
يحمل رتبة أعلى من الصف الخامس.
Appointing her Flower-Crowned General is already unprecedented.
إن تعيينها جنرالاً متوجاً بالزهور يُعدّ سابقةً غير مسبوقة.
Let alone...
ناهيك عن...
It seems the Grand Tutor's faction
يبدو أن فصيل المعلم الأكبر
still can't bear to part with that half of the military power.
لا يزال من الصعب عليّ التخلي عن ذلك النصف من القوة العسكرية.
Please reconsider, Your Majesty.
أرجو من جلالتكم إعادة النظر في الأمر.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
General Fan is no ordinary woman.
الجنرال فان ليست امرأة عادية.
She beheaded Lord Changxin and ended the war in one stroke.
قامت بقطع رأس اللورد تشانغشين وأنهت الحرب بضربة واحدة.
The primary credit belongs to her.
يعود الفضل الأكبر لها.
Discipline Inspector Li,
مفتش الانضباط لي،
be careful not to speak out of turn
احرص على عدم التحدث في غير وقته
in His Majesty's presence.
بحضور جلالته.
I heard
سمعت
that before joining the army, General Fan
أنه قبل انضمامه إلى الجيش، الجنرال فان
was a butcher girl in a border town.
كانت تعمل جزارة في بلدة حدودية.
I wonder how
أتساءل كيف
she managed to kill Lord Changxin, the bravest in the Three Armies.
لقد تمكنت من قتل اللورد تشانغشين، أشجع الجيوش الثلاثة.
Could it be...
هل يمكن أن يكون...
Thank you for the compliment, Grand Tutor Li.
شكراً لك على الإطراء، أيها المعلم الكبير لي.
I am just a village woman.
أنا مجرد امرأة قروية.
I don't know much else,
لا أعرف الكثير غير ذلك،
but I know pork must be cut precisely,
لكنني أعلم أن لحم الخنزير يجب تقطيعه بدقة،
and enemies must be killed ruthlessly.
ويجب قتل الأعداء بلا رحمة.
General Fan,
مشجع عام،
this is not your filthy pigsty.
هذا ليس حظيرة خنازير قذرة.
Now that you are a court official,
الآن وقد أصبحت مسؤولاً قضائياً،
you must watch your words and actions at all times.
يجب عليك مراقبة كلماتك وأفعالك في جميع الأوقات.
Especially in court,
وخاصة في المحكمة،
and especially before His Majesty and the Grand Tutor.
وخاصة أمام جلالته والمعلم الأكبر.
You are right, My Lord.
أنت محق يا سيدي.
Speaking of pigsties,
وبالحديث عن حظائر الخنازير،
the one at my home
الذي في منزلي
is swept clean,
يتم تنظيفها بالكامل،
and the pigs are fat and strong.
والخنازير سمينة وقوية.
But there are always some bad pigs
لكن هناك دائماً بعض الخنازير السيئة
that like to piss and shit everywhere,
تلك التي تحب التبول والتبرز في كل مكان،
making even the cleanest place dirty.
حتى أنظف الأماكن تجعلها متسخة.
You...
أنت...
Who are you calling a pig?
من الذي تصفه بالخنزير؟
Don't be angry, My Lord.
لا تغضب يا سيدي.
I didn't say you were a pig.
لم أقل إنك خنزير.
Fan, you are amusing.
يا فان، أنت مسلٍّ.
Your words are blunt,
كلامك فظّ،
but they make some sense.
لكنها منطقية إلى حد ما.
General Fan.
مشجع عام.
Sharp words do not count as military merit.
الكلمات القاسية لا تُعتبر من نقاط القوة العسكرية.
As a military commander,
بصفتي قائداً عسكرياً،
your duty is to protect the country,
واجبك هو حماية الوطن،
not to show off your sharp tongue here.
ليس الهدف هنا التباهي بلسانك اللاذع.
You are right, Grand Tutor Li.
أنت محق يا كبير المعلمين لي.
Of course I know the importance of protecting the country.
بالطبع أعرف أهمية حماية البلاد.
But when the people on the border were suffering,
لكن عندما كان الناس على الحدود يعانون،
where were you making snide remarks, Grand Tutor Li?
أين كنت تُدلي بتعليقات ساخرة يا كبير المعلمين لي؟
You...
أنت...
Alright, alright.
حسناً، حسناً.
General Fan certainly has a straightforward character,
يتمتع الجنرال فان بشخصية مباشرة وصريحة،
completely different from ordinary women.
تختلف تماماً عن النساء العاديات.
No wonder you achieved such illustrious military merits.
لا عجب أنك حققت مثل هذه الإنجازات العسكرية المرموقة.
As they say, a hero's background doesn't matter.
كما يقولون، لا يهم ماضي البطل.
We, the court officials,
نحن، موظفو المحكمة،
should be tolerant of her.
ينبغي أن يكون المرء متسامحاً معها.
As for the military power,
أما بالنسبة للقوة العسكرية،
we shall discuss it another day.
سنتناقش في هذا الأمر في يوم آخر.
Thank you, Prime Minister Wei.
شكراً لك، رئيس الوزراء وي.
That I can stand here today
أن أقف هنا اليوم
is thanks to your magnanimity.
هذا بفضل كرمك.
However, I don't think this is just a battle of words.
لكنني لا أعتقد أن الأمر مجرد معركة كلامية.
The Imperial Court is like butchering pigs.
البلاط الإمبراطوري أشبه بذبح الخنازير.
There must be rules.
لا بد من وجود قواعد.
Butchering requires a single fatal cut.
تتطلب عملية الذبح قطعاً قاتلاً واحداً.
Speaking in court should also hit the mark.
ينبغي أن يكون الحديث في المحكمة دقيقاً أيضاً.
With so much beating around the bush,
مع كل هذا التلميح واللف والدوران،
how can problems be solved?
كيف يمكن حل المشاكل؟
Just like the Battle of Lucheng—
تمامًا مثل معركة لوتشنغ—
if the soldiers had all cowered back,
لو أن الجنود جميعاً تراجعوا خوفاً،
who would have defended Lucheng?
من كان ليدافع عن لوتشنغ؟
General Fan, every word you say makes sense,
يا جنرال فان، كل كلمة تقولها منطقية.
but your language is uncouth.
لكن لغتك فظة.
You really must learn some etiquette in the future.
يجب عليك حقاً أن تتعلم بعض قواعد السلوك في المستقبل.
You are right, Prime Minister Wei.
أنت محق يا رئيس الوزراء وي.
I really need to work on my tendency
أحتاج حقًا إلى العمل على هذه العادة
to speak without thinking.
أن تتحدث دون تفكير.
Oh, right.
أوه، صحيح.
The Marquis of Wu'an asked me
سألني ماركيز ووآن
to offer incense at his parents' tomb to report his safety.
أن يقدم البخور عند قبر والديه ليطمئن على سلامته.
Prime Minister Wei,
رئيس الوزراء وي
would you like to pay respects to your sister
هل ترغب في تقديم واجب العزاء لأختك؟
and General Xie as well?
والجنرال شيه أيضاً؟
My beloved ministers,
وزرائي الأعزاء،
if there is nothing else today,
إذا لم يكن هناك شيء آخر اليوم،
court is dismissed.
تم رفض الدعوى.
Speak now or the court is dismissed!
تكلم الآن وإلا سيتم رفض الدعوى!
Farewell, Your Majesty.
وداعاً يا صاحب الجلالة.
It's a nice place,
إنه مكان جميل،
but there aren't many good people.
لكن لا يوجد الكثير من الأشخاص الطيبين.
It can't even compare to Lin'an.
لا يمكن مقارنتها حتى بلينان.
General Fan.
مشجع عام.
You shouldn't have made so many enemies in court.
كان عليك ألا تُكوّن كل هذا العدد من الأعداء في المحكمة.
Grandfather.
الجد.
So you still know I am your grandfather?
إذن ما زلت تعلم أنني جدك؟
Go back.
عُد.
General Fan, please wait.
أيها المشجع العام، يرجى الانتظار.
I am not your grandson.
أنا لست حفيدك.
What? Are you going to lecture me too?
ماذا؟ هل ستلقي عليّ محاضرة أيضاً؟
Your demeanor in the hall today
سلوكك في القاعة اليوم
truly impressed me.
لقد أثار إعجابي حقاً.
Now that you have been praised by His Majesty,
والآن وقد أثنى عليك جلالته،
and everyone calls you a heroine,
والجميع يناديك بالبطلة،
but as a woman,
لكن كامرأة،
sooner or later you must marry and have children.
عاجلاً أم آجلاً، لا بد من الزواج وإنجاب الأطفال.
No matter how high your merits are,
مهما بلغت جدارتك،
this is the ceiling.
هذا هو السقف.
A sparrow can never fly to the top branch,
لا يستطيع العصفور أن يطير إلى أعلى الغصن،
nor can it become a phoenix.
ولا يمكنها أن تصبح كطائر الفينيق.
A woman who's married and has children
امرأة متزوجة ولديها أطفال
can still achieve merits.
لا يزال بإمكانه تحقيق الإنجازات.
Besides,
بجانب،
what business is it of yours?
ما شأنك أنت بذلك؟
General Fan, have you heard the saying,
يا جنرال فان، هل سمعت بالمقولة؟
"A wise man submits to circumstances"?
"هل الرجل الحكيم يخضع للظروف؟"
Fine.
بخير.
I will now "submit to circumstances" and take my leave.
سأخضع الآن للظروف وأغادر.
My Lord.
يا سيدي.
Grand Tutor, your sedan chair is nice.
يا معلمنا الكبير، كرسيك المحمول جميل.
Getting carried away with success...
الانجراف وراء النجاح...
she'll fall hard sooner or later.
ستقع في حبه بشدة عاجلاً أم آجلاً.
My Lord!
يا إلهي!
Grand Tutor!
المعلم الكبير!
My Lord, are you alright?
يا سيدي، هل أنت بخير؟
My Lord!
يا إلهي!
How dare you...
كيف تجرؤ...
Fan Changyu.
فان تشانغيو.
Prime Minister Wei was pissed off,
كان رئيس الوزراء وي غاضباً.
and the Grand Tutor stumbled out of his sedan chair.
وتعثر المعلم الأكبر وخرج من محفته.
The Princess Royal is here!
الأميرة الملكية هنا!
Sister!
أخت!
What makes you so happy?
ما الذي يجعلك سعيداً جداً؟
[Speak with Caution]
[تحدث بحذر]
Do you know General Fan came to court today?
هل تعلم أن الجنرال فان حضر إلى المحكمة اليوم؟
She is truly an extraordinary figure.
إنها حقاً شخصية استثنائية.
Let me tell you, Sister.
دعيني أخبركِ يا أختي.
Since I ascended the throne,
منذ أن اعتليت العرش،
I have never laughed as heartily as I did today.
لم أضحك قط من قلبي كما فعلت اليوم.
Tell me,
أخبرني،
[Speak with Caution]
[تحدث بحذر]
what kind of person is she?
ما نوع الشخص الذي هي عليه؟
Changyu...
تشانغيو...
Changyu has a straightforward nature.
تشانغيو يتمتع بطبيعة صريحة.
She is honest and adorable.
إنها صادقة ورائعة.
Her martial arts are outstanding.
مهاراتها في فنون الدفاع عن النفس رائعة.
She is sincere to her friends
إنها صادقة مع أصدقائها
and willing to die for her comrades.
ومستعدة للموت من أجل رفاقها.
And towards the Marquis of Wu'an, she is...
وهي تجاه ماركيز ووآن...
How is she towards the Marquis of Wu'an?
كيف هي علاقتها بماركيز ووآن؟
Do not reveal my relationship with Changyu after returning to the Capital.
لا تكشف عن علاقتي بتشانغيو بعد عودتي إلى العاصمة.
I fear someone might use it to cause trouble.
أخشى أن يستخدمه أحدهم لإثارة المشاكل.
She holds the Marquis of Wu'an in high esteem.
إنها تُكنّ احتراماً كبيراً لمركيز ووآن .
They are comrades-in-arms.
إنهم رفاق سلاح.
So, this Fan Changyu can not only fight,
إذن، هذا فان تشانغيو لا يستطيع القتال فحسب،
but also influence Xie Zheng.
بل ويؤثر أيضاً على شيه تشنغ.
I was worried that there was no one I could use in court.
كنت قلقاً من عدم وجود أي شخص يمكنني الاستعانة به في المحكمة.
This girl suits my needs perfectly.
هذه الفتاة تناسب احتياجاتي تماماً.
Grandfather,
الجد،
although Qi Min is a royal grandson,
على الرغم من أن تشي مين هو حفيد ملكي،
he is not a worthy lord.
إنه ليس سيداً جديراً.
He is perverse and violent,
إنه منحرف وعنيف،
and his methods are vicious.
وأساليبه شريرة.
If our Li family helps him regain imperial power,
إذا ساعدته عائلة لي على استعادة السلطة الإمبراطورية،
when he comes into power,
عندما يتولى السلطة،
it will be a time of suffering for the common people.
سيكون وقتاً عصيباً على عامة الناس.
Now, Qi Sheng
الآن، تشي شنغ
is merely Wei Yan's puppet.
إنها مجرد دمية في يد وي يان.
He is unworthy of his position and incompetent.
إنه لا يستحق منصبه وهو غير كفؤ.
As for Wei Yan's nature—
أما بالنسبة لطبيعة وي يان—
you don't need me
أنت لست بحاجة إلي
to tell you.
لأخبرك.
In past wars,
في الحروب السابقة،
he completely disregarded the lives of the people,
لقد تجاهل تماماً أرواح الناس،
forcibly requisitioning grain.
الاستيلاء على الحبوب بالقوة.
The people were starving and displaced.
كان الناس يتضورون جوعاً ونازحين.
The tragic scene of starved corpses littering the fields
مشهد مأساوي لجثث متضور جوعاً تملأ الحقول
was all caused by him.
كل ذلك كان بسببه.
Such behavior
هذا السلوك
is truly cruel and inhumane.
إنها حقاً قاسية وغير إنسانية.
That is what truly makes the people suffer.
هذا هو ما يجعل الناس يعانون حقاً.
But Qi Min's cruelty
لكن قسوة تشي مين
far exceeds that of Wei Yan.
يتجاوز بكثير ما حققه وي يان.
I saw it with my own eyes.
رأيت ذلك بأم عيني.
Grandfather,
الجد،
our Li family has been loyal for generations.
لقد كانت عائلة لي عائلة وفية لأجيال.
We must not help a tyrant do evil
لا يجوز لنا أن نساعد طاغية على فعل الشر
and let such a despicable person ascend the throne.
وليصعد مثل هذا الشخص الحقير إلى العرش.
But he is the descendant of Crown Prince Chengde,
لكنه سليل ولي العهد تشنغده،
bearing the legitimate blood of the imperial family.
يحمل الدم الشرعي للعائلة الإمبراطورية.
All these years,
طوال هذه السنوات،
he has been wandering and suffering hardships.
لقد كان يتجول ويعاني من المصاعب.
It is inevitable that his temperament has become unstable.
لا مفر من أن مزاجه أصبح غير مستقر.
You should try to understand him
ينبغي عليك أن تحاول فهمه
and not judge him rashly.
وعدم الحكم عليه بتسرع.
Haven't you thought about
ألم تفكر في
that we might be cast aside once we've served our purpose?
هل يمكن أن يتم التخلي عنا بمجرد أن نؤدي غرضنا؟
Grandson,
حفيد،
your Master, He Jingyuan,
سيدك، هو جينغيوان
was principled and righteous.
كان صاحب مبدأ وصالح.
He was a top-tier meritorious official of Great Yin.
كان مسؤولاً رفيع المستوى ومتميزاً في مملكة يين العظمى.
He died fighting on the battlefield!
لقد مات وهو يقاتل في ساحة المعركة!
In the end, it was all for nothing.
في النهاية، كان كل ذلك بلا جدوى.
No matter how much you emphasize national righteousness,
مهما بالغت في التأكيد على النزاهة الوطنية،
what good will it do?
ما الفائدة المرجوة من ذلك؟
Then you shouldn't have sent me to the Northwest in the first place.
إذن كان يجب ألا ترسلني إلى الشمال الغربي من البداية.
Think it through.
فكر في الأمر جيداً.
Is the current Emperor
هل الإمبراطور الحالي
a wise ruler or a tyrant?
حاكم حكيم أم طاغية؟
Is he beneficial
هل هو مفيد؟
to the nation?
للأمة؟
My Lord.
يا سيدي.
Have men surround the study immediately.
اجعل الرجال يحيطون بالدراسة فوراً.
If he dares to act rashly,
إذا تجرأ على التصرف بتهور،
confine him at once
احتجزه مرة واحدة
and then report back to me.
ثم أبلغني بالنتيجة.
Yes.
نعم.
Qi Min has been taken care of.
تم الاعتناء بـ تشي مين.
He is right at...
هو محق في...
[Jingque Pavilion]
جناح جينجك
Come here.
تعال الى هنا.
My Lord, what are you doing?
يا سيدي، ماذا تفعل؟
Stop it, My Lord.
توقف عن ذلك يا سيدي.
Where are you going?
إلى أين أنت ذاهب؟
We haven't finished the wine yet.
لم ننتهِ من شرب النبيذ بعد.
Don't run away, little lady. Little lady!
لا تهربي يا صغيرتي. يا صغيرتي!
My Lord.
يا سيدي.
General Fan, come in and join the fun.
يا مشجعي الجماهير، تفضلوا بالدخول وانضموا إلى المرح.
Yeah, General Fan, come on in.
أجل، أيها المشجع العام، تفضل بالدخول.
No thanks. You guys enjoy.
لا، شكراً. استمتعوا أنتم.
Well...
حسنًا...
My Lord,
يا سيدي،
come catch me!
تعالوا أمسكوا بي!
Alright, alright.
حسناً، حسناً.
Socializing? What does socializing mean?
الاختلاط الاجتماعي؟ ما معنى الاختلاط الاجتماعي؟
It means hanging out with a bunch of strangers,
يعني ذلك قضاء الوقت مع مجموعة من الغرباء،
eating and drinking.
تناول الطعام والشراب.
After that, you become acquaintances.
بعد ذلك، تصبحون معارف.
Why don't you socialize with me a bit?
لماذا لا تختلط بي قليلاً؟
Socialize with me.
تواصل معي اجتماعياً.
[Jingque Pavilion]
جناح جينجك
General Fan.
مشجع عام.
General Fan, until next time.
إلى اللقاء يا مشجع عام.
Until next time.
إلى اللقاء في المرة القادمة.
-My Lord, let me see you off. -My Lord, you're not drunk, are you?
يا سيدي، دعني أودعك. يا سيدي، أنت لست ثملاً، أليس كذلك؟
Come again next time.
تفضل بزيارتنا مرة أخرى.
Sure, sure.
بالتأكيد، بالتأكيد.
Let's go, Fan.
هيا بنا يا فان.
I'm going for a walk.
سأذهب في نزهة.
You guys go ahead.
انطلقوا يا رفاق.
Don't forget me.
لا تنساني.
I won't.
أنا لن.
Clothes.
ملابس.
Wait here.
انتظر هنا.
I'll go take a look.
سأذهب لألقي نظرة.
♪ The moon is as quiet as me ♪
♪ القمر هادئ مثلي ♪
♪ The light shines ♪
♪ النور يسطع ♪
♪ It illuminates the turbulence in my heart ♪
♪ إنها تُنير الاضطراب في قلبي ♪
♪ It seems to be the fire of love ♪
♪ يبدو أنها نار الحب ♪
♪ Just a few sparks ♪
♪ مجرد شرارات قليلة ♪
♪ Let me hide in your heart ♪
♪ دعني أختبئ في قلبك ♪
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
I missed you.
أفتقدك.
♪ I pray that our love ♪
♪ أدعو أن يكون حبنا ♪
♪ Will never end ♪
♪ لن ينتهي أبداً ♪
♪ It's worth my foolishly waiting ♪
♪ يستحق الأمر انتظاري الأحمق ♪
♪ For a lifetime ♪
♪ مدى الحياة ♪
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ واضح وهادئ مثلي ♪
♪ Why do we need to seek cause and effect ♪
♪ لماذا نحتاج إلى البحث عن السبب والنتيجة ♪
Aren't you afraid of being seen?
ألا تخاف من أن يراك أحد؟
It doesn't matter.
لا يهم.
I was worried since it's your first time in the Capital.
كنت قلقاً لأنها زيارتك الأولى للعاصمة.
But seeing how
لكن رؤية كيف
our Flower-Crowned General handled things with ease,
لقد تعامل جنرالنا المتوج بالزهور مع الأمور بسهولة.
I was relieved.
شعرت بالارتياح.
None of the officials
لم يكن أي من المسؤولين
care about the truth
يهتم بالحقيقة
from 17 years ago.
منذ 17 عامًا.
Those stories in the shadow puppet plays,
تلك القصص في مسرحيات خيال الظل،
about voicing grievances before the throne and getting justice,
بشأن التعبير عن المظالم أمام العرش والحصول على العدالة،
where good and evil are judged,
حيث يُحكم على الخير والشر،
are all fake.
كلها مزيفة.
And the Emperor is unreliable.
والإمبراطور لا يُعتمد عليه.
Don't worry.
لا تقلق.
I'll go with you to find the truth.
سأذهب معك للعثور على الحقيقة.
We will clear your father's name.
سنبرئ ساحة والدك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Let's go home.
هيا بنا إلى المنزل.
Go home? We won't wait for Sister?
نعود إلى المنزل؟ لن ننتظر أختنا؟
Didn't you say there are many bad people in the Capital?
ألم تقل أن هناك الكثير من الأشخاص السيئين في العاصمة؟
Shouldn't we protect her?
ألا يجب علينا حمايتها؟
Right.
يمين.
Today in the Golden Celestial Hall,
اليوم في القاعة السماوية الذهبية،
the Emperor asked Sister if she had a husband.
سأل الإمبراطور أخته عما إذا كان لديها زوج.
What does he want?
ماذا يريد؟
That bastard Emperor.
ذلك الإمبراطور الوغد.
He definitely wants Sister to be his consort.
إنه بالتأكيد يريد أن تكون أخته قرينته.
He can't have any good intentions.
لا يمكن أن تكون لديه أي نوايا حسنة.
You're catching on.
أنت تفهم الأمر.
Stop babbling here.
توقف عن الثرثرة هنا.
With the Marquis of Wu'an here,
بوجود ماركيز ووآن هنا،
no one in this world can hurt her.
لا أحد في هذا العالم يستطيع أن يؤذيها.
You're worrying for nothing.
أنت تقلق بلا داعٍ.
Pointless. Truly pointless.
لا طائل منه. لا طائل منه حقاً.
Go back.
عُد.
I'll take a walk by myself.
سأتمشى بمفردي.
[Prudent in Action, Mindful of Peril]
[حكيم في العمل، متيقظ للمخاطر]
Greetings, Your Majesty.
تحية طيبة يا صاحب الجلالة.
Dear ministers.
أيها الوزراء الكرام.
What do you have to report to me?
ما الذي يجب عليك إبلاغي به؟
Your Majesty, I have a matter to report.
جلالة الملك، لدي أمر أود الإبلاغ عنه.
That Flower-Crowned General, Fan Changyu,
ذلك الجنرال المتوج بالزهور، فان تشانغيو،
is arrogant and oversteps her bounds,
إنها متغطرسة وتتجاوز حدودها،
a disgrace to the integrity of Great Yin.
عار على نزاهة يين العظيم.
She not only contradicted Prime Minister Wei,
لم تكتفِ بمعارضة رئيس الوزراء وي،
but was also disrespectful to me.
لكنه كان أيضاً غير محترم معي.
Your Majesty, I hope you will punish her.
يا صاحب الجلالة، آمل أن تعاقبها.
Prime Minister Wei, are you also here to impeach General Fan?
رئيس الوزراء وي، هل أنت هنا أيضاً لعزل الجنرال فان؟
No, Your Majesty.
لا يا جلالة الملك.
I am here to request a reward for General Fan.
أنا هنا لأطلب مكافأة للجنرال فان.
Didn't you mention the rumors
ألم تذكر الشائعات؟
about the former Eastern Palace a few days ago?
بخصوص القصر الشرقي السابق قبل بضعة أيام؟
I have investigated it thoroughly.
لقد قمت بالتحقيق في الأمر بدقة.
General Fan not only
ليس فقط المشجع العام
killed Lord Changxin on the battlefield,
قتل اللورد تشانغشين في ساحة المعركة،
earning great merit,
استحقاقاً عظيماً،
but she also saved the bloodline of Crown Prince Chengde,
لكنها أنقذت أيضاً سلالة ولي العهد تشنغده،
the Imperial Great-Grandson.
حفيد الإمبراطور الأكبر.
He is the legitimate grandson of the former Eastern Palace.
هو الحفيد الشرعي للقصر الشرقي السابق.
General Fan has achieved a great merit this time.
لقد حقق الجنرال فان إنجازاً عظيماً هذه المرة.
Her bravery should be commended.
ينبغي الإشادة بشجاعتها.
What... joyous news for the nation.
يا لها من أخبار سارة للأمة.
Prime Minister Wei,
رئيس الوزراء وي
the imperial bloodline concerns the legitimacy of the state.
يتعلق النسب الإمبراطوري بشرعية الدولة.
It cannot be confused.
لا يمكن الخلط بينهما.
Seventeen years ago, the Eastern Palace caught fire.
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً، اشتعلت النيران في القصر الشرقي.
Crown Princess Chengde and the legitimate Imperial Grandson both died.
توفيت ولية العهد الأميرة تشنغده والحفيد الإمبراطوري الشرعي .
So,
لذا،
how could this Imperial Great-Grandson appear out of nowhere?
كيف يمكن أن يظهر هذا الحفيد الإمبراطوري من العدم؟
And where is he
وأين هو؟
now?
الآن؟
After the battle of Lucheng,
بعد معركة لوتشنغ،
the Imperial Great-Grandson indeed went missing.
لقد فُقد حفيد الإمبراطور الأكبر بالفعل.
I request a decree to issue a bounty
أطلب إصدار مرسوم بمنح مكافأة لمن يقبض على من يقبض عليه.
to search for the Imperial Great-Grandson throughout the country.
للبحث عن حفيد الإمبراطور الأكبر في جميع أنحاء البلاد.
If we can truly find the imperial bloodline this time,
إذا استطعنا حقاً العثور على السلالة الإمبراطورية هذه المرة،
it would relieve Your Majesty's worries about succession.
من شأن ذلك أن يخفف من مخاوف جلالتكم بشأن الخلافة.
As for whether he is real or fake,
أما بخصوص ما إذا كان حقيقياً أم مزيفاً،
there must be ways to verify it.
لا بد من وجود طرق للتحقق من ذلك.
Even if there is a slight chance,
حتى لو كان هناك احتمال ضئيل،
we cannot give up.
لا يمكننا الاستسلام.
Only in this way
بهذه الطريقة فقط
can we be worthy of the late Emperor's vast grace.
هل يمكننا أن نكون جديرين بكرم الإمبراطور الراحل العظيم؟
Prime Minister Wei, you're right.
رئيس الوزراء وي، أنت محق.
As for the bounty,
أما بالنسبة للمكافأة،
I entrust you to handle it.
أعهد إليك بالتعامل مع الأمر.
You must... You must find...
يجب عليك... يجب أن تجد...
my poor nephew.
ابن أخي المسكين.
Grandfather, please calm down. Watch your health.
يا جدي، من فضلك اهدأ. انتبه لصحتك.
Does the Marquis of Wu'an really have luck on his side?
هل حقاً يحالف الحظ ماركيز ووآن ؟
He clearly committed heinous crimes,
لقد ارتكب جرائم شنيعة بكل وضوح،
but they keep getting cancelled out.
لكنها تستمر في التلاشي.
No.
لا.
No matter what,
مهما حدث،
I must make this uncle and nephew
يجب أن أجعل هذا عمًا وابن أخ
completely turn on each other!
ينقلبون على بعضهم البعض تماماً!
Send someone immediately
أرسل شخصًا على الفور
to get word to Xie Zheng by any means necessary.
إيصال الخبر إلى شيه تشنغ بأي وسيلة ضرورية.
Tell him that 17 years ago,
أخبره بذلك قبل 17 عامًا،
on the way returning to the capital,
في طريق العودة إلى العاصمة،
Wei Yan received a letter from Qi.
تلقى وي يان رسالة من تشي.
That caused the deaths of his father, Xie Linshan,
وقد تسبب ذلك في وفاة والده، شي لينشان.
and Crown Prince Chengde of the Eastern Palace.
وولي العهد تشنغده من القصر الشرقي.
But that letter has long since disappeared.
لكن تلك الرسالة اختفت منذ زمن طويل.
That bastard Wei might have destroyed it.
ربما يكون ذلك الوغد وي قد دمرها.
A rumor is all we need.
كل ما نحتاجه هو مجرد إشاعة.
Xie Zheng will look for the evidence.
سيبحث شيه تشنغ عن الأدلة.
We just need to let the two of them
كل ما علينا فعله هو السماح لهما بذلك
fight it out.
قاتلوا حتى النهاية.
Seventeen years ago,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً،
Wei Yan was a man of many attachments.
كان وي يان رجلاً ذا علاقات متعددة.
That's why it led to today's great catastrophe.
ولهذا السبب أدى ذلك إلى الكارثة الكبرى التي نشهدها اليوم.
Today,
اليوم،
let's just
لنبدأ فقط
set up another trap.
نصب فخاً آخر.
[Post-Credits Scene]
[مشهد ما بعد نهاية الفيلم]
[Where Compassion and Grace Meet]
[حيث تلتقي الرحمة والنعمة]
Your Majesty, I am here!
جلالتكم، أنا هنا!
I knew it!
كنت أعرف!
Of all the officials at court,
من بين جميع المسؤولين في المحكمة،
not a single one treats me
لم يعاملني أحدٌ منهم معاملة حسنة.
as the true Emperor!
بصفته الإمبراطور الحقيقي!
Wei Yan treats me like a puppet.
يعاملني وي يان كدمية.
Does Xie Zheng also want to do the same—
هل يرغب شيه تشنغ أيضاً في فعل الشيء نفسه؟
find a descendant of the former Eastern Palace
العثور على أحد أحفاد القصر الشرقي السابق
and use him as a puppet?
واستخدامه كدمية؟
Li Xiang, you... you are useless!
لي شيانغ، أنت... أنت عديم الفائدة!
You even missed the information
حتى أنك أغفلت المعلومات
that the former Eastern Palace has a descendant
أن القصر الشرقي السابق له سليل
still alive in this world!
ما زلت على قيد الحياة في هذا العالم!
Even you...
حتى أنت...
Do you also want to
هل تريد أنت أيضاً
serve a different emperor?
هل يخدمون إمبراطورًا مختلفًا؟
Do you?
هل أنت؟
No!
لا!
Please calm your anger, Your Majesty!
أرجو منك أن تهدأ من غضبك يا جلالة الملك!
Do not let my mistakes
لا تدع أخطائي تؤثر عليّ
harm your health.
يضر بصحتك.
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
I have really tried my best this time.
لقد بذلت قصارى جهدي هذه المرة.
The Princess Royal wouldn't help me either.
لم تساعدني الأميرة الملكية أيضاً.
With no other choice,
مع عدم وجود خيار آخر،
I risked my life to break into that military tent.
لقد خاطرت بحياتي لاقتحام تلك الخيمة العسكرية.
But...
لكن...
I had an ear cut off by His Lordship!
لقد قطع سيدي أذني!
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
I know I am useless.
أعلم أنني عديم الفائدة.
But...
لكن...
in my heart,
في قلبي،
truly,
حقا،
there is only you, Your Majesty.
أنت وحدك يا ​​صاحب الجلالة.
Come forward.
تقدم للأمام.
I am here.
أنا هنا.
Does it hurt?
هل يؤلمك؟
I... I am fine.
أنا... أنا بخير.
It's better now.
الوضع أفضل الآن.
N-No matter if it's Wei Yan...
لا يهم إن كان وي يان...
or Xie Zheng,
أو شيه تشنغ،
no one can sit on this dragon throne!
لا أحد يستطيع الجلوس على عرش التنين هذا!
It is mine!
إنه ملكي!
No one else can!
لا أحد غيري يستطيع!
Yes, Your Majesty.
نعم يا جلالة الملك.
You are the true Son of Heaven.
أنت ابن السماء الحقيقي.
Those people are not worthy!
هؤلاء الناس لا يستحقون!
No, you... you promise me
لا، أنتِ... أنتِ تعدينني
that you will serve me for the rest of your life.
أنك ستخدمني لبقية حياتك.
That I am the Emperor.
أنا الإمبراطور.
Yes,
نعم،
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!